Finding aid to the Karl Scott Putnam Papers CA.MS.00347
Smith College Archives
Karl Scott Putnam Papers
1910-1978
Smith College Archives
Putnam, Karl Scott, 1883-1965
CA.MS.00347
1.667 linear feet (4 containers)
Professor of Architecture. Contains correspondence, clippings, notes, publications, syllabi, sketches, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Karl Scott Putnam was born on April 28, 1883 in Leverett, Massachusetts to Roswell and Sarah Putman. In 1910, Putnam graduated from the University of Pennsylvania with a Bachelors of Science, and attended graduate school at the Columbia University School of Architecture. After graduation, Putnam worked for architectural offices in Boston and New York. He moved to Northampton, Massachusetts in 1913 to begin his own practice. Constructing many homes within the Pioneer Valley, Putnam commonly designed homes within the classical, New England vein. That said, he also designed homes that were considered modern for the time period. Putnam's most famous client was President Calvin Coolidge, as he designed two of his homes. Oliver Carlton, President of the Northampton Historical Society in the 1960s, said Putman's "buildings were always a place for people." Beginning his tenure at Smith College in 1929, Putnam was an associate professor of Architecture until his retirement in 1952. He held the title of Professor Emeritus until his death in 1965. Putnam also taught at the Cambridge School of Architecture, which was purchased by the college under President William Allan Neilson. During his professorship at Smith, Putnam was contracted by the college to design many buildings throughout campus. Included in the buildings he designed for the college are the Quadrangle, the Crew House, the Field House, and Scott Gymnasium. In addition to his work for the college, Putnam was Director of the Northampton Historical Society from 1943-1953, and was President of the New England Architectural Society for a number of years. He also served as a visiting Professor at the University of Massachusetts from 1949-1950. Putnam was married to Mabel (Cratts) Putnam, with whom he had a daughter named Ruth Ann Jackson. Karl Scott Putnam died in 1965 at his home in Northampton, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains correspondence, clippings, obituaries, course materials, notes, publications, and lists of buildings designed by Putnam. Also included in the collection are various building plans, including contracts, estimated costs, sketches, photographs, and details regarding materials used. The collection also contains materials relating to Raymond Putnam, including a song written in honor of his retirement and drawings given to him by Claire Manwell.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Karl Scott Putnam papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Putnam, Karl Scott, 1883-1965
- Biographical Information
  - General, 1937-1978; undated (Box 978, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1958; undated (Box 978, Folder 2)
  - Obituaries, 1965-1966 (Box 978, Folder 3)
- Project Materials
  - Building notes, 1956-1964; undated (Box 978, Folder 4)
  - Contract specifications, 1922 (Box 978, Folder 5)
  - Contract specifications, 1943-1963 (Box 978, Folder 6)
  - Mitchell house, undated (Box 978, Folder 7)
  - Notes and slide lists, 1943-1944; undated (Box 978, Folder 8)
  - Potter house, Route 9, undated (Box 978, Folder 9)
  - Sketches, 1960; undated (Box 978, Folder 10)
  - Misc. notes on useable materials, 1934-1964; undated (Box 978, Folder 11)
  - Misc. photos and lists of work projects, 1930-1946; undated (Box 978, Folder 12)
  - Raymond Putnam: drawings by Claire Manwell, undated (Box 978, Folder 13)
  - Raymond Putnam: retirement song, 1963 (Box 978, Folder 14)
- Course Notes
  - 1940s, 1950s, 1960s,1970s up to Centennial (1975), undated (Box 979, Folder 1)
  - 19th Century England, 1954; undated (Box 979, Folder 2)
  - America: 18th Century/ Late Georgian, 1932; undated (Box 979, Folder 3)
  - America: South Carolina, North Carolina, Virginia, Maryland, D.C., 1910; undated (Box 979, Folder 4)
  - American Art 77, a. 1940; undated (Box 979, Folder 5)
  - American Bulfrinch, Shranguin, Benjamin, Blesserman, 1931; undated (Box 979, Folder 6)
  - Art 12 (Sem. 1)-Key, 1939-1940 (Box 979, Folder 7)
  - Art 12 (Sem. 1)-Key, 1940-1941 (Box 979, Folder 8)
  - Art 12 (Sem. 2)-Key, 1940-1941 (Box 979, Folder 9)
  - Art 22 (1800s), 1936-1946; undated (Box 979, Folder 10)
  - Art 22 (Early Christian Art and Architecture), 1921-1940; undated (Box 979, Folder 11)
  - Art 22 (Sem. 1)-Key, 1936-1937 (Box 980, Folder 1)
  - Art 22 (Sem. 2), 1936-1937 (Box 980, Folder 2)
  - Byzantine, undated (Box 980, Folder 3)
  - Classical Revival, undated (Box 980, Folder 4)
  - Colonial and Queen Anne Restoration, undated (Box 980, Folder 5)
  - English: Medieval, 1934-1951; undated (Box 980, Folder 6)
  - French Medieval Art, undated (Box 980, Folder 7)
  - French Renaissance, 1935-1940; undated (Box 980, Folder 8)
  - German Medieval Art, 1936; undated (Box 980, Folder 9)
  - Germany: Modern Architecture, undated (Box 981, Folder 1)
  - Gothic Revival in England 18th Century Costumes, undated (Box 981, Folder 2)
  - Greece, 1934; undated (Box 981, Folder 3)
  - Medieval and Gothic Architecture, Gothic Tradition in America, 1931-1940; undated (Box 981, Folder 4)
  - Principles of Architecture, 1942-1948 (Box 981, Folder 5)
  - Renaissance Italy, 1929-1939; undated (Box 981, Folder 6)
  - Rome, undated (Box 981, Folder 7)
  - Unlabeled course notes, 1935-1942; undated (Box 981, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous class notes, undated (Box 981, Folder 9)